Speaker 1: The 13th century
Guns were invented by the Chinese.
The first guns were quite large, like small cannons.
The oldest gun that still exists today was made in about 1280.
Glasses were invented by the Italians in about 1286.
Sunglasses were invented even earlier, in the twelfth century.
Speaker 2: The 18th century
The hot-air balloon was invented by two French brothers, Joseph and Jacques Montgolfier.
The first flight with people was in 1783, and the balloon flew three kilometres over Paris.
Speaker 1: The 19th century
Stamps were invented by an English teacher, Rowland Hill.
The first stamp, from 1840, was called the Penny Black,
and it showed the head of the young Queen Victoria.
The saxophone was invented by a Belgian musician in 1846.
His name was Adolphe Sax.
Saxophones were first used mainly in military bands,
but are now used in all kinds of music.
Speaker 2: The 20th century
The biro was invented in the 1930s by a Hungarian journalist, Laszlo Biro.
His invention was successful because the ink from the pen dried very quickly on paper.
In 1943, Biro moved to Argentina because of the war in Germany, and he died there.
The word ‘biro’ is now the most used name for any ballpoint pen.
Lego was invented in 1932 by a Danish businessman, Ole Kirk Christiansen.
The name Lego comes from the Danish phrase leg godt, which means ‘play well’.
Twenty billion pieces of Lego are produced every year.
CDs were invented by a Dutch company, Philips, in 1970.
Sony also worked on CDs, and they were designed to play 74 minutes of music
because that was the length of Beethoven’s Ninth Symphony – the Sony boss’s favourite piece of music.
The mobile phone was invented by an American company.
It was first produced by the company Motorola.
On 3rd April 1973, Martin Cooper,
a Motorola researcher and executive, made the first mobile telephone call.
His phone weighed one point one kilograms.
Speaker 1: The 21st century
The virtual assistant Siri was invented by three American engineers in 2010.
They later sold it to Apple for $200 million dollars.
It speaks, recognizes voice commands,
and can do things like answer questions, turn things on and off, and pay bills.
The voice of Siri is provided by different actors in different countries and,
in addition to male and female voices,
in 2022 Apple added a gender-neutral voice option called Quinn.